Hypotheses which are at the edge of our
understanding can be enlightening.
>> This is Ryan Williams. He's a professor
at MIT who won the Gödel Prize for
theoretical computer science, and I
started by asking him a LeetCode
question. So, the question is three-sum.
Can you do better than n squared for
this?
>> Yeah, you actually can do better than n
squared, and this is um not at all
obvious.
>> He also had contrarian takes on popular
hypotheses.
>> I think I'm on the record as not
believing this hypothesis. We really
don't understand polynomial time
computation as deeply as we think we do.
>> All right, I want to start by asking you
the most popular LeetCode question. So,
the question is three-sum.
Given a list of numbers, and we want to
find three numbers such that they sum to
zero.
>> Yes.
>> And so, what are your thoughts on the
brute-force solution for this? We can
start there.
>> So, the obvious brute-force solution
takes if you you've got n numbers n
cubed time. Just try all the triples of
numbers, sum them up, see if they sum to
zero. There is a faster uh solution. So,
one way to get
an order n squared time algorithm for
three-sum is to first start by sorting
the numbers.
And then, you go through the numbers one
by one. Say like, you're looking at a
number A.
And you want to know,
is there a B and a C in the rest of the
list um
whose sum with A is going to be zero?
Okay, so,
the way
this works is
after you sort the numbers, you you do
what's called a finger search. So, you
put um
the finger from your left hand on the
minimum element and finger from your
right hand on the maximum element. So
you start there. And you check like,
okay, are these my B and C?
Right? So you you add them min and max
and check if adding that with A gets you
zero. Okay?
And um if you're lucky, okay, then
you're done, but typically you're not
lucky. And so this sum of the min and
the max is either
um larger than your target value minus A
or it's smaller.
Okay? If it's larger, then you need to
decrease the larger number. So you take
your right finger, which is sitting on
the maximum element, and you move it to
the left one slot. Okay? So you decrease
the larger one.
All right? If the sum is smaller than
your target, you need to take the
smaller number and make it a little bit
bigger. So you move the you move your
left finger sitting on the minimum over
one slot. Okay? And you you keep doing
this. You keep checking
whether, you know, your left finger and
right finger are pointing at a solution.
And if they aren't, then you adjust it.
If they do, they ever do sum up to
exactly what you want, you're done.
And so after each comparison like this,
right? One of your fingers moved. Okay?
If the fingers ever cross, then you
don't have a solution. Like there's just
there just can't be a solution.
And so the number of times you move, you
know, your fingers in total is like N.
So so you have a order N solution for
finding that extra pair.
And you do this for each of the numbers
A.
Okay? So then you get a order N squared
uh solution overall. You do it N times.
Each finger search
uh takes order N time.
>> And that is the popular solution. think.
>> solution, yes.
>> of people know when we're in these
algorithmic LeetCode interviews.
And I know a lot of your research is
kind of about pushing lower bounds, so
maybe we can
start that conversation off by can you
do better than n squared for this?
>> Yeah, you actually can do better than n
squared. And this is um
uh not at all obvious.
In in fact, it it stems from
um taking this finger search idea and
pushing it in a different direction.
So, what you do is you take your sorted
list, okay, and you
break
uh the sorted list up into little groups
of contiguous elements. So, let's say
your little group is like log n size or
square root log n. It's like a really
small little group, okay?
So, you've got either n over log n
groups total or n over square root log n
groups total depending on how you
break up your groups.
And then the idea is you're going to
perform the same kind of finger search,
but you're going to set things up so
that you're comparing two pairs of
groups. Your finger's always pointing at
an entire group.
So, like the left hand and right hand
are pointing at two groups and you want
to know if there's a three sum solution
in that group.
And
you can set up a kind of fast data
structure to check a small group, okay?
And this data structure will take much
less than
um the number of elements in the two
groups squared. So, you set up some
kind of fancy data structure. And
because you set your group size so
small, it's like a pre-processing that
you do over all the possible
inputs you could send from a pair of
groups.
And so, you have some data structure and
it will, you know, let's say it takes
you n to the 1.5 time to prepare this
data structure, this fancy data
structure. But now, when you're looking
at
a pair of groups,
you can look at the answer much faster
than what finger search would have
taken. I guess finger search through
like a group of length G and another
group of length G would take about order
G time, and you can do actually do
faster by by this kind of look up. This
kind of table look up. I think it is
kind of like you you take
uh
this list of length N
and you
uh kind of shrink it into like N over
num uh N over N over group size uh
number of things. And these are more
complicated objects.
And then you do And now like you you're
trying to you're trying to speed up like
the check over these like small uh
complicated objects. For like, should I
move my finger to the right? Like, is
there nothing in this group? Would
finger search just just go straight
through this group or not? Is basically
what you're asking.
>> So, the unit that you're operating on is
not a single integer, it's a
a group.
>> Yeah, it's like a group of them. So, you
use some kind of table look up. Uh
And so, well, it's it's it's much
fancier than a table look up, actually.
It's
It goes through some other model called
the linear decision tree model. Like, so
it's like in some weird model where you
can actually get a faster three some
solution. You can get a N to the 1.5
solution. And there's It's a really
interesting and sophisticated solution,
but what I want to emphasize is it
starts from
the finger search solution. And sort of
like figuring out how to like
process finger moves faster.
Uh sort of do pre-processing so that
finger moves can can go faster.
>> Yeah, I saw the the time complexity
this. It's N squared divided by
log N divided by log log N all raised to
the 2/3.
What Is there any intuition behind I
mean, that's just crazy.
>> So, there are several algorithms of this
kind, and they all work by doing some
modification on what I was talking about
because you can sort of reduce to a
different model. Like a like a
a different kind of look up table, a
different kind of set of tricks.
And you know, maybe there is some
savings you can do here and there by
sort of compressing things a little
differently. Um so, that yeah, there are
several algorithms that beat the n
squared running time bound,
and they all, to my knowledge, kind of
work in a similar type of of way. Like
they
they're they're taking this n squared
time algorithm and finding little ways
to like pre-process
and then optimize like based on the
pre-processing. Like make finger
searches faster and things like that.
Sort of yeah.
>> A lot of your research is on this this
topic of fine-grained complexity or kind
of lowering lower bounds. So, um maybe
you can explain
what is fine-grained
>> Lowering lower bounds, I like that.
>> Yeah, lowering
>> [laughter]
>> Um the idea behind fine-grained
complexity is we have a variety
of problems, canonical problems that
we teach to undergrads.
Um we have canonical algorithms for
these problems. These algorithms have
resisted any major improvements in
decades, and so, we wonder, are these
algorithms optimal?
And what does a theory of optimality
look like in terms of time complexity?
So, what if we just focus solely on the
time complexity of a problem? Like the
fastest algorithm that will solve that
problem.
What does complexity look like then?
Because like P versus NP is not about
time I mean, it's about time complexity
but on a coarse
grained level where P is just
polynomial time. But that polynomial
could be n to the 10 into the billion
whatever and so like showing that
something's not in P is is showing that
it needs some super polynomial amount of
time. Whereas here we we are concerned
with there's a canonical problem it
takes
n cubed time with some very
elegant canonical algorithm. We want to
know
could you do any better? Could you
improve that exponent to n to the 3
minus epsilon for some epsilon?
And then you ask, well
suppose I have a problem over here
and it has a quadratic time algorithm.
And I want to know
if I can improve that quadratic time
algorithm by a little bit. Then you
start asking questions like, well,
suppose I improve this algorithm by a
little bit.
Can I improve this algorithm over here
by a little bit?
And this is naturally a notion of
reduction like saying that like
I want to have some reduction from
problem A to problem B
so that if I can improve the algorithm
for problem B just a little bit
then I can also improve the algorithm
for for problem A by just a little bit.
This actually leads to a different
notion of complexity. You can even take
an NP-complete problem
and a P problem
and reduce the NP problem to the P
problem and the question still makes
sense.
So
for example,
uh you could talk about the subset sum
uh problem, okay? So the subset sum
problem
you've uh got n numbers
and a target value.
And you want to know if there's a subset
of those numbers that sum to a
particular target value, okay?
Now you got n numbers, there's two to
the n possible subsets.
The obvious algorithm takes two to the n
time.
Okay?
But you can actually do better than
this. And the way you do better than
this is to reduce to a polynomial time
solvable problem.
So,
you can get a algorithm which runs in
square root of 2 to the n time for the
subset sum problem. You can avoid
enumerating over all the possible
subsets in a substantial way. And this
is in fact known um
commonly in cryptanalysis by
um I guess a like a meet in the middle
uh type approach. Like So, people do
this sort of thing all the time.
The idea is you partition the set of all
the numbers into two halves, n over two,
n over two.
You enumerate all the subset sums on the
two halves. So, you have 2 to the n over
two possible sums for like the first
half, 2 to the n over two possible sums
for the second half. Then you want to
know, is there a number from the first
half,
you know, from this huge list,
plus another number from the second
half, this huge list, that sums to the
target.
Now, this is the two sum problem.
This is really nothing more than the two
sum problem, which you can solve by
sorting
and binary search.
And this is a reduction. We have shown
how to solve a subset sum problem
like which would normally take 2 to the
n time
in square root of 2 to the n time. An
NP-complete problem by reducing it to a
problem like two sum. The obvious
algorithm there takes n squared time
trying all the pairs of numbers to see
if they sum to a target, and using an n
log n time algorithm for that.
So, so fine-grained complexity can
can relate problems that would not be
relatable at all in the traditional P
versus NP theory. Like one problem is NP
complete, the other problem is not, so
they
they should not have a polynomial time
reduction between them, like in general,
right? But so but if you just look at
the time complexity and you focus on
okay, I have an algorithm, 2 to the n
algorithm, is it the best possible?
Then um
and then I have a n squared algorithm,
is it the best possible? And you then
you can relate the two problems.
And this is a general phenomenon that
you can relate problems that look
like they should have nothing to do with
each other.
>> So you talked about
you talked about reducing subset sum to
two sum
and but subset sum is n arbitrary
integers that sum to
the target sum, right?
>> Yeah, so the idea is um
nobody said I had to use a polynomial
time reduction or something like that to
reduce one problem to another.
So so what's what happened what happened
the trick was I took this subset sum
problem that had n numbers
and then I blew it up
to an instance of this two sum problem.
But that two sum problem has about
square root of 2 to the n numbers.
Now I can solve two sum in linear time.
So that so solving that instance gives
me a square root of 2 to the n time
algorithm for the original problem.
But yeah, in in the meantime, going from
one problem to the other, I blew it up.
And I but by blowing it up, I I'm able
to improve the time complexity of the
obvious algorithm for subset sum.
>> I get it. Okay, so the reduction
it it's kind of like the
if you solve the subset sum, you have
some time complexity, and if you
translate it to the other problem, you
lose a little bit of time complexity,
but less than the aggregate.
>> So all you want to make sure is when all
the dust is cleared and settled, you
want to be able to say, "Look, if I can
improve
the obvious algorithm for two sum,
then I can improve the obvious algorithm
for subset sum." And that's what this
thing achieves.
Right? Because I know because I know how
to get a faster algorithm for two sum,
I can get one for subset sum. So, so you
just want your your reduction between
two problems to have this property. If I
can improve
one problem by a little bit in running
time, I can improve the other problem by
a little bit.
>> In one of your talks, you you mentioned
preserving magic between Okay, so this
is that.
>> this is exactly like preserving magic
because
>> Well, I mean,
>> once you see the two sum solution, it's
not so magical anymore. But, imagine
>> [laughter]
>> that you didn't know about sorting and
binary search and the like, and someone
just says, "Find a pair of things with a
certain property, and there are n
things."
And you're like, "Well, I mean, all the
number of possible pairs
is about n squared, so maybe it'll take
me n squared."
In this particular case, because they're
numbers and you're summing them,
there's an n log n time algorithm. It is
a It is a surprise when you first see
that no, you don't have to try all of
the pairs of numbers. There is a
shortcut. There is a clear shortcut that
lets you find a pair much faster.
And then, you can use that uh
surprise um
or magic, if you will, and get something
for a subset sum. Get a algorithm for
subset sum that avoids trying all of the
two to the n subsets.
>> So, I understand one of the the driving
motives for pursuing this, I guess,
lowering of lower bounds
is that
um
strong exponential time hypothesis, or I
see it, you know, SETH.
Um could you explain that and its
significance?
>> Strong ETH is like a severe
strengthening
of the P versus NP question.
So,
P versus NP
is um, asking whether the SAT problem
um,
has a polynomial time algorithm or not.
Right? And
strong ETH
is basically saying that
for the SAT problem,
uh, you cannot solve it
faster
than much faster than two to the end.
So, there's no 1.999
to the end time algorithm.
For every string of nines, there is no
1.9999 to the end time algorithm.
Um, to say the hypothesis totally
precisely, it has to do with the K-SAT
problem
and you're looking at
clauses of
length K for arbitrary K, but
um,
those details don't matter so much. It's
a canonically NP-complete problem. SAT
is solved all the time in practice. It's
extremely useful for a verification
nowadays. It's an It's an engine
for verification. Um, so it can be
solved fairly well in practice.
However, in the worst case, we still
don't know how to solve it uh,
significantly faster than two to the
end.
So, the hypothesis that it needs, say,
1.99999
to the end time for all strings of nines
is a very strong
exponential time hypothesis. It's way
stronger than P versus NP. It says, "Uh,
no, no, no, no. It's not super
polynomial. It's actually darn near two
to the end time that you need."
Right?
>> And so, do you think that hypothesis is
true and you know, why or why not?
>> I think I'm on the record as not
believing this hypothesis. Yeah. Um
Yeah, why don't I believe this
hypothesis?
Um
Well, I started thinking about this
hypothesis
maybe already as an
undergrad, but certainly starting
in grad school.
Like early in grad school I was thinking
about this. So, before it was even
called strong ETH, I guess that shows
how old I am.
I was trying to think about how to solve
the so-called CNF SAT problem faster
than 2 to the n.
And
well, at the time
there were a number of other NP-complete
problems that had faster algorithms like
subset sum.
So, I thought, well, there's not I mean,
what's so special about SAT? Like, if
all these other problems have faster
algorithms um why not SAT as well? Like
if you restrict to the 3-SAT problem
like So, this is where
you have an AND of these clauses, each
clause has like is an OR of three
variables some of the variables may be
negated.
You want to know if there's a way to set
all the variables to make all the
clauses simultaneously true. Um there is
a faster algorithm for that.
Um but this is a more general version of
SAT. Um
So, at first I just thought, well,
there's no good reason to think in a
lower bound these other related problems
have upper bounds.
So, why not?
But then
um over time I would have different
attacks
on strong ETH, like trying to refute it.
Always trying to refute it in different
ways, these attacks would fail
in some completely catastrophic and
ridiculous way, like um they would like
have no chance of
actually solving the original problem.
But by sort of staring at my failure and
trying to think, well, there's something
interesting happening here. What can I
do with this? Like there's something
interesting. Yeah, it doesn't refute uh
the strong ETH thing.
What does it do? So, by trying to pivot
and and figure out, okay, what can I do
with my failure?
I was able to solve a like a variety of
other problems instead.
And so, after a while, I realized the
truth value
of strong ETH to me
is almost irrelevant. Like because if I
believe that it's false, then I get good
ideas.
I get I get good ideas. Like
And so, by trying to think about, okay,
what would an algorithm that breaks
through the end look like? What could it
look like?
I I sort of force myself to think in a
different way.
Like I I I have to like discard
other natural algorithmic possibilities
because we know they they won't work.
Um
and I have to think in a in a different
direction. And and so,
because it kind of like sends my brain
in a different direction, sends me
thinking a different way,
it's very useful for research.
You know, you you
I mean, even even though I still haven't
refuted it or whatever, like it's very
useful for me to believe that it's
false. Like operationally.
So, the truth value, well, I mean
I believe this is a minority opinion,
right? Why why would they go against I
mean, I think um
for example, Russell and Piazzo, good
friend of mine who uh, helped propose
this.
I mean, he always emphasizes to me,
"Well, this this is a hip hypothesis.
It, you know, we didn't We explicitly
did not name it a conjecture."
We wanted to sort of put forth
some lower bound that would get you to
think about it. Like something that's
maybe a little more controversial than
the other types of things like P = NP or
whatever. Or, you know, like other
things that people more nor- normally
believe. So, like hypothesis, which are
at the edge of our understanding,
can be enlightening to think about. Like
where we truly don't know what the
answer might be based on our intuition.
Um,
so this this is, I guess, one reason why
it was
proposed, but one reason why you might
believe that strong ETH is true is
because believing it implies a lot of
other lower bounds for you conveniently
because you can reduce the SAT problem
to a bunch of other problems that seem
totally unrelated like edit distance,
um, various pattern matching problems.
Um, they have natural
polynomial time solutions if you can
improve on the algorithms for any of
those, you would improve the one for SAT
as well. You would get something better
than 2 to the n. So, believing in it
sort of makes a convenient world view.
It shows that all these different
textbook algorithms are indeed optimal.
>> We've talked about SAT or we've
mentioned SAT so many times in this
conversation. I know there's so many
forms of that problem. What are all the
different forms? And I know there's
there's clause width, also this idea of
depth, too.
>> Um, the most common
representation of a of a SAT formula is
the conjunctive normal form, so-called
CNF representation. And this is what
modern SAT solvers get as input. They
They get their file in in so-called
DIMACS CNF form. And this is
just every line of my file, I give you a
list of
uh variables, possibly with negations,
and each one is a clause. And I'm
supposed to take the or
of those uh
uh variables or negations. These are
Variables or negations, they're often
called literals. Okay, so I take an or
of these literals.
And
the width
of that clause is the number of literals
in it.
Okay?
And
um I'm supposed to take the and over all
those lines, each line in my DIMACS CNF
file.
And so it's an and
of a bunch of ors, and each or has
some small number of literals in it.
Call it K. So usually the the width is
called K.
And so the K-SAT problem is to find an
assignment to all the variables that
satisfies all the clauses when each
clause has width K
or width at most K.
It could be smaller.
Um so that's the most popular
uh version. That's what
SAT solvers, you know, turn on.
And that's what is behind uh strong ETH.
That's the representation there.
Um but there are other ways uh to
represent
a Boolean formula. You could just simply
represent it as some arbitrary
expression
made out made up of ors and ands and
negations. It could just be some
arbitrary expression with nested
parentheses
and all that mess. Um
you could ask you know, given a formula
in this representation with a bunch of
variables, is there a way to set the
variables to make this true? That's
formula SAT.
Um, you could also look at
at circuits of bounded depth, as you
mentioned. So,
there is this
um, this class of circuits that people
study
called uh AC uh circuits for alternating
circuits. Um, it doesn't mean
alternation in terms of electricity, it
means alternation in terms of
uh ORs and ANDs. So, these circuits are
made up of uh ORs and ANDs like in
layers. So, the CNF representation is a
special case where I have an an AND
of ORs like uh
like a AND of a bunch of clauses and
then ORs of the literals.
But, you can go further. You can have an
AND of OR of ANDs
of variables with negations and things
like that. And so, these are uh constant
depth AC circuits. And because the idea
is
uh you only have some constant number of
layers of these ANDs and ORs. And you
can look at the SAT problem
on circuits like that as well, for
example. Those are Those are two
uh other versions that people look at.
>> Yeah, strong ETH is on K-SAT, and I saw
on less than or I guess, you know,
2-SAT, 3-SAT, 4-SAT, 5-SAT. There exists
solutions that are asymptotically better
than 2 to the N. So, I guess it it you
know, the
the larger K can be, the more difficult
the the problem is.
>> That That is the intuition.
>> I'm curious, have you ever plotted that
curve? Like, is it Does it drop off, you
know, exponentially or
>> Yeah. Yeah. Um, th- yeah, that's what's
so interesting uh about the current
state of the art in K-SAT algorithms. As
K increases,
all of them
all of the different types of algorithms
you might try to run, they all approach
a 2 to the n exponent. Like, as K grows
and grows and grows, they get 1.99,
1.999, and so on. And yeah, it it drops
I mean, it get In other words, it will
like it goes towards
uh pretty quickly
actually. And like so we we understand
like how the exponent behaves pretty
well for the known algorithms we have.
>> And then um for for something like
3-SAT, what is the intuition behind
speeding up an exponential time search?
>> Yeah, so for 3-SAT, um
let's just look at a a single clause,
okay? A clause that's got
three variables in it, okay?
We know that if
uh if we set all those three variables
wrong, it's going to be false. Okay, so
we have to avoid one of those
assignments, okay?
Well, that means that there are seven
out of the eight possible assignments,
so there's like three variables,
two to the three, eight possible
assignments, seven of them could be a
satisfying assignment. They uh they
could be part of a satisfying
assignment, we don't know. But one of
them is definitely not.
So the one easy way to see that 2-SAT
can be solved in less than 2 to the n
time is just take any clause,
try one of the seven possible
assignments,
and plug them in,
and then recurse
on the remaining formula.
Now, let's think about what we did. If
we were just trying all the possible 2
to the n assignments,
and we we would like plug in,
you know,
uh one of eight possible assignments
for each of those three variables. And
so we'd have eight recursive calls.
Well, we instead, because we're clever
and we looked at the clauses, we have
seven recursive calls.
And that that's the difference. So so we
reduced
by three variables at the cost of seven
recursive calls as opposed to eight.
And this gets you a slight improvement.
This gets you about
uh 1.9
two to the end.
Something slightly better than
than
uh two to the end.
Okay, but you can do better than this.
Um
But this is this is sort of like the
idea. You try to look at ways to plug in
variables that will force constraints so
you can rule out a large portion of the
possible assignments.
>> When I was thinking about circuits, it
and you know, the different widths and
depths, I I don't know if this is uh
unusual question, but it it reminds me
of neural nets, but the operators are
different and the space of the
uh the literals is different. So instead
of booleans, it's maybe floating points.
And so it just made me wonder about uh
the algorithms that you might apply on a
neural net. Is there, you know, analogs
in between these two spaces?
>> Yes. Yes. So
um
Yeah, if we look at
say I want to model a neural network
on So I want to compute say it's still a
boolean function,
but I want to do it with like a neural
network. So like I want to
use, let's say
uh relus or
um sign activation functions or or what
what have you. Um
There is
a slightly more general like gate that
we can use instead of ors and ands. That
turns out to basically be equivalent.
So, if instead of using ORs and ANDs, we
use a so-called majority gate,
which outputs one if and only if at
least half of its inputs are one.
Using this and negations, we can
actually simulate
uh neural nets, like the usual types of
neural nets that you think of with the
usual types of activation functions. So,
if they have a constant number of layers
of neurons, we can get a constant number
of layers
of majority gates and and negations.
So, once you go So, this is so-called TC
circuits for threshold circuits.
Uh yeah, so once you allow threshold
circuits, you can start to model uh
neural networks.
>> Still using booleans. It's just
>> We're still looking at boolean inputs
though, yes. So, once you allow your
input space
to
to be larger and like have floating
points, then
um you can you can prove a lot
uh
more in terms of lower bounds. You can
find like things that take like depth
three
in a neural net that's, you know, can't
be done in depth two and so on.
Um
So, yeah, once you go
past that and you start looking at just
arbitrary real domain, it it becomes a
a a totally different picture than from
a discrete domain.
>> OpenAI, Anthropic, Cursor, and Vercel
all use this product to make their lives
better.
And the problem it solves is when you're
building SaaS or an ad product and you
want to sell to other companies, there's
all these requirements you need to meet.
There's SSO, there's SCIM, there's RBAC,
there's audit logs. These are all things
that take time to integrate, but aren't
the main focus of your app. WorkOS is an
API layer that lets you meet all of
these requirements in just a few lines
of code. So, let's say you have a new
SaaS product and you want to sell to
other companies, WorkOS will solve all
of these critical feature gaps for you.
You can check them out at workos.com to
learn more and get started. And I
appreciate them for supporting my work
and sponsoring this podcast. One topic I
thought might be fun to go over is you
you wrote this paper about the
likelihoods of these various conjectures
in complexity theory and
I I pulled a few of these that were kind
of a minority opinions or maybe, you
know, less less common takes. So, I'm
curious to hear your rationale. So,
>> [laughter]
>> uh one of them the well-known one, you P
P not equal to NP or, you know, P versus
NP.
Um
you assigned an 80% confidence that
they're not the same. And I think most
people say much higher confidence. So,
why do you why would you assign such a
low confidence that they're not the
same?
>> It's interesting because I think I
originally had something like
75%
but then uh my college classmate Scott
Aaronson was like, "How dare you?" kind
of you know,
he was
>> [laughter]
>> he was he he sort of called me out and
I'm like, "Okay, fine. For you 80%
fine."
I guess that my point is that
we really don't understand polynomial
time computation
as deeply
as we think we do. And
there are
surprises like all the time
in the power of algorithms.
There are very few surprises in terms of
lower bounds. Like, when we are able to
prove a lower bound,
typically it's something we
very much expected to be true
but it was hard to prove. It was hard to
prove.
Somehow we pulled it off, we got what we
expected to be true.
But all the time in algorithms
people are finding algorithms where
it's just like surprising. Just
Wait. What? How How do you get something
that fast? You're right. So
uh this just happens over and over.
When I was younger
um when I was first thinking about P
versus NP
I
like I had an intuition for what should
be.
And
what I've understood over the years is
that
my intuition for what should be
is often just wrong. And I'm I'm having
to revise my intuitions uh all the time.
So when something like this happens
often enough
you start asking yourself, "What do I
really understand?
Uh do I really understand P versus NP?"
Like I mean, I understand the the the
statement, right? Like it's just one of
those problems where
somehow it is not so difficult to to
make formal, to write down
mathematically.
But to actually know what the answer is
is just orders of magnitude more
difficult than it is to phrase the
problem. And complexity theory in
particular is littered with
statements like this where
um
the the space of algorithms is just that
vast. Um
so if you just if you're just keep
getting surprised over time, you're just
like, "Well, what
what do I understand?" Maybe it was just
misplaced confidence.
>> Okay, what about this one? So
EXP not equal to NEXP or would you say
NEXP?
>> Oh, NEXP. Yeah. EXP versus NEXP. So this
is like the exponential time
of P versus NP.
>> For X not equal to NX or NEXP,
you gave it a 45% chance. And if this is
>> [laughter]
>> the P not equal to NP
equivalent, but for exponential time,
why is your
>> Yeah.
>> Why is it so low?
>> Oh, because exponential time algorithms
are even more powerful.
Did I really say 45%? I mean,
>> You did.
>> versus X or NX versus co-NX.
>> Yeah, NX not equal to X 45%.
>> [laughter]
>> I have it.
It's in this table.
>> So, so in other words, I believe NX
equals X more
than I believe they're different, right?
So,
um yeah, let me try to explain why. So,
you can think of the NX versus X
question
as
um some special case
of P versus NP,
where instead of looking at the
arbitrary SAT problem,
I'm looking at a SAT problem which is
extremely compressible.
So, there's like a really small little
computer
that is exponentially smaller than the
length of the instance, and it just
outputs the character
uh on the line number and the column
number for the for the DIMACS CNF, like
the the CNF file, okay? So, it's like a
extreme compression
of like some file.
So, it's like you zipped it down to like
something like exponentially smaller
than its original length, okay?
So, it's like some super compressed,
extremely highly regular
SAT instance. So, I give you that, and I
ask you,
uh when you unpack this thing,
decompress it,
is the result going to be satisfiable or
not?
And I want you to solve this
in time polynomial in the decompressed
representation.
Okay.
Okay. So, the point is that like this is
SAT, but
in the some very special case where the
thing is extremely structured.
So, the idea
um one conjecture for why SAT solvers
work
um
in practice.
Like one I mean this is
I mean conjecture maybe overkill because
I mean this is just this is not even a
well-formed mathematical statement. So,
one hypothesis for why SAT solvers work
in practice is because
um the real world is highly structured.
The real world is governed by physical
laws
that are not random. They're not
arbitrary. Like from a very small number
of rules, we can recreate so much of
science.
So,
what arises in practice from designs of
hardware and things like this are often
extremely compressible. They have to be
extremely compressible.
And
so maybe it's true that you know, every
uh SAT which has
uh a highly compact representation can
just be solved uh efficiently. This is
This is the idea of whether, you know,
NEXP equals EXP.
Um that it when it's really really
structured like that and super
compressible, there is some advantage.
It's not like a completely random and
since it's not like something arbitrary,
it's No, it's in fact very very special.
>> The other one is 80% likelihood on NEXP
equal to coNEXP,
and you wrote why would a
self-respecting complexity theory do
that?
>> [laughter]
>> Yeah, I was curious why that's such a
contentious statement.
>> So, NEXP versus coNEXP. Let's Let's
first talk about NP versus co-NP.
So, co-NP
um
is like the class of sort of complements
of NP-complete problems like
like UNSAT, like checking whether
something's UNSAT.
Now, from the time complexity point of
view
there's no difference between checking
SAT and UNSAT. You can always flip the
answer.
But from the complexity point of view,
if I if I ask you does co-NP equal NP?
What I'm asking you is, could you prove
to me
that a formula is unsatisfiable
with a short proof?
When it's satisfiable I can give you a
short proof. I can just give you the
satisfying assignment. You plug it in,
check that it works. But if it's
unsatisfiable, if there no assignment
works
we're saying for all assignments
the formula is not true. Can you flip
that to an existential statement and
say, "Oh, there exists this little proof
makes it work." So
people don't believe that NP is equal to
co-NP
and in fact like NP different from co-NP
implies P different from NP.
Um
But so this is the exponential time
version
of NP versus co-NP. So it's co-NEX
uh
versus NEX.
The reason why I think
these are likely to be equal
is that
if a little birdie
sat on an NEX machine's shoulder and
gave it a little bit of advice
about what the co-NEX thing is doing
then
the an NEX
uh algorithm
can actually solve co-NEX problems.
And so let let me explain
uh let me explain why Yeah, what's the
little birdie What the heck is the
little birdie saying? So
because NEX problems can run in 2 to the
end time and two to the N squared time
and things like that.
Running an exhaustive search over all
possible inputs of length N is no
problem
for NX.
So, what a little birdie can do is say,
"Okay, suppose um
like I want to verify that
this particular
um instance
like let's say let we can talk about
like an unsat but like the you know some
compressible unsat problem or something.
Suppose I want to prove that this
compressible unsat instance
um
is a yes. Okay? How am I going to do
that uh
with NX?
The little birdie will tell me
the total number of inputs of length N
which are a yes.
Okay?
So, it it will it will just tell me some
string which says, "Here's the total
number of inputs of length N. You gave
me a length N input. Here's the total
number of inputs of length N
uh
that are a yes. Okay?
Okay? So,
um this this advice this little you know
birdie's advice doesn't take very much
like to encode a count. It's like order
N bits to encode a count uh of things.
So,
um so, what does the NX thing do to
prove a co-NX thing? What it does is it
guesses
the things which are a no.
So, I'm trying to prove unsat. So, unsat
means yes, sat means no.
So, the NX thing guesses those things
which are no.
The no things it can answer, right? If
it's a sat thing, it can just guess the
answer to each of the nos.
Okay?
So, it guesses the answer to each of the
nos. It verifies all those answers, and
then it checks that the number of things
it guessed is what the birdie told it.
Once it's done that, all the no's have
been covered, so everything else must be
a yes.
So that so so it can actually prove a
yes by just exhaustively finding all the
no's and ruling out any other no's.
>> But the big question in my mind is where
do you get the little birdie?
>> Where do you get the little birdie
advice from? Yeah, yeah. So
yeah, so this I studied yeah, this um
what the little birdie gives you
and it seems to me that it it is
possible that this little birdie itself
can be constructed in NX.
And if so, then we'd just be done. Like
in NX, you figure out what the little
birdie would tell you and then use that
to just flip the answer. So it guess
Let's sort of guess all the things which
are no, so what remains must be a yes
and
we talked a lot about time
>> complexity. And you mentioned a little
bit this advice I guess kind of space
complexity. And I know you had a major
result relating space and time
complexity. You're basically simulating
time complexity with space complexity,
but lower than it's been done prior.
Could you explain
what it was before your breakthrough
result and then maybe the intuition
behind your breakthrough result?
>> Uh in general, the problem is the
following. I give you
an algorithm that runs in time T
and I want to know
um is there another algorithm that uses
space much less than T? Uses amount of
memory like you know, units of memory
much less
than T
and still solve the problem completely.
Still completely simulates the thing
perfectly.
Um
one intuition for why you
might think um
this
question just
can't be solved or some problems there's
just no
way to improve on the spaces if you
think of like
the pro like a lot of problems in
dynamic programming like let's say I
have
um
some logic circuit that I want to
evaluate and all of the gates are
provided to me in a row and all the
wires sort of flow from left to right.
And the you know I start with
information on the left.
I want to compute the information on the
far right.
And all the you know all the bits are
flowing left to right by wires.
The natural way to evaluate such a
circuit is you start with say the inputs
on the left.
For each gate in turn in the the line
you look at its inputs. Its inputs have
been determined if there's some bits.
You use that to compute the value of
that gate. You pass the values of that
of you know the output of that gate
forward.
Okay?
But if
that uh circuit you know has
T gates in it you know it will take
about T time to solve but it will
definitely also take about T space in
general.
All right? Like the circuit could be
wired up in some wild way and there just
might not be a way to save uh space for
an arbitrary uh circuit.
But already in 1975
people were studying this kind of of
question and finding counterintuitive
answers to it.
So
um Hopcroft, Paul, and Valiant uh based
on work of Patterson and Valiant
uh showed that
time T algorithms at least in this
so-called multi-tape Turing machine uh
model very powerful model uh can be
simulated in space T divided by log of
T. So I mean it's like a like you you
get some space savings but it's only
like a log T factor. Okay.
Um
and
the way this is done is is quite
counterintuitive. Uh it was I mean like
even though there's a only a log factor
there it was
uh
pretty shocking.
That development was
extended to random access models of
computation
um later
and and in more general models of
computation. So like in in the late '70s
and early '80s.
Um
so so it was known for like a pretty
much any reasonable model of computation
that time T can be simulated in space
about T over log T.
But there was a hidden maybe not so
hidden um gotcha in the space efficient
simulation. It needs
an exponential amount of time
to run. So like you there's a time space
trade-off. Okay, if you really want to
save some space you got to blow up the
time by a lot.
Nevertheless
um yeah, it was kind of commonly
conjectured that
this T over log T space was about the
best you could do and you
and that you were probably not going to
get T to the 0.9
space or you know something something
much more efficient. Um
so yeah, it was a big surprise to me uh
like that you can actually put time T in
space about square root
of T.
Again, there's an exponential
running time just to you know give the
full caveat out there.
But
um
but it's still very surprising. Like
this holds for
any kind of time T
uh algorithm. Like, including something
that might be outputting, you know,
something pseudo random, some you know,
something from cryptography,
you know, like it's not at all obvious
that every such process could be
compressed
to only be need like square root of T
uh space and still get the job done,
still compute whatever function was
being computed.
>> I mean, I know it's probably super
involved, but if you could just a high
level, what's the trick? How'd you do
it?
>> Well, the trick for me was to read
um James Cook and Ian Mertz's paper on
tree evaluation very, very carefully.
That
I mean, and just knowing um the P the
landscape around P versus P space and
knowing what Hopcroft, Paul, and Valiant
did. Um
Yeah, so but I I can give you a very
high-level idea of
kind of what's going on and how what
they did uh is useful.
So,
Hopcroft, Paul, and Valiant, the way
they were modeling
uh space-bounded computation was in a
particular way that seemed pretty
general uh at the time, but turned out
to be restrictive
uh
in ways that we just didn't anticipate.
So, the way they thought of it was
um I'm going to take like certain I'm
going to break the computation up into
little pieces
and I'm going to
like write I'm going to write pieces of
the computation like little bits into
the memory, but I'm only going to do
that over blank space. I mean, this is
something that sounds natural, right?
Like, so like I'm going to erase pieces
of memory and then I'm going to
overwrite that blank space with a piece
of memory. So, I'm being very
destructive in a certain sense. Like but
this is a natural thing you do, right?
Like if you want to replace you know,
swap something with something else,
you often just erase. But there are ways
to swap
without uh erasing, right? So, there's
like a common
little trick that is taught in uh CS
courses.
So, like if you
um if you require everything to be
written into a blank uh
register,
then if you want to swap the contents of
two variables like X and Y,
then you've
you've got to have a temporary register.
Like you move one into the temp, you
erase it, you move Y into the
into there and then so on, right?
But if you don't want a temp, you can
achieve the same thing uh with just
XORing the the registers bitwise. Or if
you've got numbers, you can add and
subtract, okay? In three instructions,
clever instructions, adding,
subtracting, or XORing,
you can actually swap the contents of
two registers without needing a third.
Okay? This is kind of the starting point
for thinking about like, well, why does
it matter
if you're always writing into erased
memory?
So,
so what
uh
James Cook and Ian Mertz showed
uh at a very high level was
they they were studying a certain
problem
called tree evaluation, whatever that
is,
and they were the problem had an
algorithm where you're all you had a
little stack
and you're always sort of like
um you know,
popping and and uh pushing on the stack,
but you were always, you know, writing
uh
writing computation contents into erase
memory, okay? What they realized was
that if you allow computations to XOR
bits of memory into existing memory,
then you can save a lot of space.
So, if you're really, really careful
about how you XOR things, you can
basically recover uh you like what's in
your memory without storing all of it at
once. You sort of offload things to
computation,
and you XOR on top of things very, very
cleverly. You can get like nice
cancellations of things you don't want,
and and keep around things you do want.
Yeah, so
I mean, that is a high-level uh idea of
how this stuff works. And then going to
square root, is it just an extension of
that, or is it a completely different?
So, the the way it works with square
root, a square root just happens to be
kind of like the optimal trade-off
in this uh tree evaluation business. So,
so
um what you do is you break the
computation into square root of T time
intervals,
and each time interval has about square
root of T
um steps in it.
And then what you do is you you give a a
particular way of simulating this thing,
so that you're only kind of holding
about a constant number
of blocks or like of these time
intervals in memory at any point in
time.
Like you're only holding a small number
of these
uh
time intervals, like a records of time
intervals in memory at any any point in
time.
Which is entirely not obvious how you
would do it. But but it's some sort of
like it's some sort of sweet spot to set
the square root of T. It's a way to It's
like the
the minimum setting of like trade-off.
Like say I have like
I want to break the computational
intervals, and the intervals have a
certain number of steps. If I If I set
it to be square root of T, then the
number of intervals and the number of
steps in each interval is about the
same.
>> So, I mean, that was a long-held result.
I mean, you you mentioned it was 1975.
That's maybe Yeah, almost 50 years where
if you come up with something like that
and you you I guess you're writing it
out, you're thinking through, and then
you see it. What is that moment like?
>> So, I you know, I'm I've been around
long enough to have been deceived by
myself many many many many times.
So,
yeah, I guess the the first two or three
times I thought about this,
um
I just thought this is another one of
those ideas that can't possibly work.
There's no way. There's just no way this
works.
Um
so, I would just kind of leave it
and then come back to it sometimes when
I was
bored of whatever else I was working on.
Um
like I I It was a pretty slow process of
convincing myself that this could
possibly be true. Like, I
I thought there was
either a bug in what
James and Ian
was doing somewhere,
or there was a bug in
my interpretation of what's happening.
Um I thought
there had to be a mistake for a long
time.
And the only way I got over that was
just
writing it down
uh over and over and over in different
ways, sort of writing and rewriting and
writing and rewriting and adding more
detail,
and then maybe finding a different way
of explaining it and it erasing and, you
know, writing something shorter,
and just sort of re-explaining it to
myself over and over and over.
And even then, like when I submitted it
to the
um stock conference where it was where
it appeared, um I wasn't entirely
confident that it was correct. I was
just exhausted from like thinking about
it for so long and just thought that
maybe someone else will find the mistake
for me. Like I'm Like I Like I At this
point, like
I I was just like desperate. Like I had
actually sent it
to two
colleagues that I trust,
you know, privately and asked them,
"Can you help me find the mistake?" Or
whatever. "Can you help me understand
this?" And one of them just said, like
they Basically, they just didn't read
past the abstract. They're like, "I'm
not I'm sorry. I'm not going to
I'm like they just didn't believe it,
period. Just like me. I mean, they
didn't believe it.
And
uh another one said,
after a long time, "Well,
I didn't quite
um
follow it, but
there was a footnote that you put
like in in the bottom of some page.
After that after that footnote,
then I began to believe it."
So then what I did was I just took that
footnote and elaborated it in in like a
later revision, sort of made it the what
I called the warm-up. I'm going to
because I was like, yeah, I I've got to
do I've got to write this thing in a way
that is airtight so that other people
will actually believe believe this
because
yeah, I it took me a long time to get
used to it, to believe it. Yeah.
>> Wow. Uh what What motivates you to solve
these
hard problems? I mean, what keeps you
driven? Cuz you kind of sounds like you
got to just bash your head against the
wall and
maybe you get there, maybe you don't.
>> I try not to bash my head against the
wall. Um and if I'm going to do it,
it's going to be, you know, a
comfortable wall. It's going to be, you
know, when it's like
high-end and luxurious or something.
Like I'm going to enjoy
uh the process is what I mean. Like if
if I don't enjoy the process of really
grinding and trying to understand
something,
I'm just I'm not going to do it. Like uh
So, I think that
if, you know, if anything is
uh one thing that I that I like I I like
to involve myself in
working on problems where
the the grind is actually joyous and and
fun. Yeah. Um for the other things, uh
they're just they're mainly
opportunistic. They're mainly me just
taking something that new that I see and
just fully integrating it with
everything I know and following
everything to the logical conclusion.
And just seeing what happens. Like and
not not trying not to get emotional,
trying not to whatever, just trying to
follow everything one step after
another. Yeah.
How do you pick good research direction?
The best kind of research direction,
which is very hard to um
it's very hard to come across,
is a direction where you
you've set yourself up in a way that you
can't lose.
That like I have a hypothesis
H
and one of two things is going to
happen. Like either I
prove H is true
or I refute H, prove not H. What I would
like to have is a situation where
um if H is true,
then good things happen. If not H is
true,
good things still happen. Other other
good things. Like um the I like I like
to look at things where Yeah, it's a
win-win.
Kind of if if you can
find opportunities like this, this is
important. Like I think often I'm not
looking at a specific uh problem.
I'm looking at a method. I'm looking at
the technique.
You know, I'm looking at not the
specific proof, but like like the space
of ideas, and I'm trying to understand
what else can be done in the space of
ideas.
Like so so often I solve problems just
by by just taking some idea and putting
it somewhere somewhere else.
>> Do you have a concrete example of where
you you've pursued something knowing
that if you succeed, good. If you
succeed in other direction, also good.
>> I have some particular research program
for which if it materializes, would
actually
show that something called the
orthogonal vectors problem
can be solved in nearly linear time.
Okay? Now,
this um
Now, if that's true, then the SAT
problem can be solved
in about the same time as subset sum. It
could be solved in like square root of 2
the n. So, this would like
truly break uh strong ETH in like a
radical way. Okay?
And
um
I did a lot of work uh in the past
showing how if
uh you can improve on the running time
of SAT,
then you can somehow use that
to prove circuit complexity lower
bounds. You can take an algorithm for
analyzing circuits
that's non-trivial and interesting and
turn that into a limitation on what
those circuits can compute. Okay?
So
So this hypothesis
Let me Maybe maybe I won't exactly say
what it is. It's It's a pretty
technical statement, but the point is
that if the hypothesis is true
then I get this fantastic algorithm for
this orthogonal vectors problem. I get
this algorithm for SAT. I get circuit
complexity lower bounds from that. I get
to somehow prove limitations on what
circuits can do.
If the hypothesis is false
I can use that hypothesis to actually
show another circuit complexity lower
bound of a different flavor.
So So regardless of whether or not like
the hypothesis is true or false, like
I'm going to make progress in complexity
theory. I'm going to prove a new
limitation one way or the other.
Right? So
it So sometimes like I mean this can be
difficult to do, but um
usually what has happened instead of
something so clean
is that I have
I I read about some idea
or whatever. I try to apply the idea. I
read about some magical algorithm. I try
to apply the magical algorithm to solve
something like SAT.
It doesn't work. But I look at my
approach. I stare really hard at it. I
try to pivot. You know, I try to
just extract what I can, and then I get
some other type of algorithm.
Right? I mean, this is essentially how I
proved
um
like the circuit complexity lower bounds
that that first got me a job at Stanford
was I was trying to solve SAT faster
with some algorithm. It didn't work, but
then I realized that that algorithm
worked for a large class of circuits,
including ones we didn't know lower
bounds for.
So then I used that to prove
a lower a lower bounds.
Yeah. so I mean
um this is just a general principle that
that I've had.
>> What would be your book recommendation
if someone wants to learn more on
complexity theory?
>> Yeah, so it sort of depends on how deep
uh
you want to go. There's Avi's book.
Yeah, Avi's book is really nice. If
you're looking for something a little
more gentle of an introduction,
um
I would say like you could read the
early chapters of Lance Fortnow's uh The
Golden Ticket.
Like trying to imagine what a world
would be like if P equaled NP.
Um I it I I like that imagination
exercise that that Lance uh
did.
On a more technical level, you know, if
you're looking um
for something slightly more technical,
you could look at The Nature of
Computation by um Mertens and Moore,
I think. So, this is
this is
still
uh not, you know, very technical, but
um but a lot but it is a textbook,
right? Yeah, um
and then of course
uh
Sipser's uh Introduction to the Theory
of Computation is like
um a fairly concise and very
well-written uh textbook. Yeah.
>> Last question for you is if you could go
back to the beginning of your career
knowing what you know now, what advice
would you give yourself?
>> So, I guess like one thing that I did
um by accident, I guess, uh which I
think
uh people
should keep in mind is that you don't
need uh permission
to work on very tough problems. Like
in fact, the tougher the problem, like
in complexity theory, there are all
these problems where
like, really nobody
has a very good clue of what to do
beyond like a few
simple structural results. Like,
so that kind of levels the playing field
a bit and
yeah, like you just you don't need
permission to think about these
problems. You don't need like, you know,
anybody's uh say-so or whatever.
Um
I mean, that's that's one thing that I
would would like younger people uh to
keep in mind that I mean, this knowledge
is open to the world and it's open to
you and and you can just go learn it and
think about it and
you don't Yeah, you don't need any
anybody's permission, especially not
mine. Um
Yeah, like
um another thing
I think is uh to avoid inertia
in the sense that like, you know, if you
if you don't think about
and reflect like, where am I going
and what am I doing?
Um
you can, you know, you can just end up
coasting in a certain direction.
And I think it's important for people to
sit down and truly reflect and think
from time to time
like, okay, if I keep going in this
direction
is this going to lead to a place that I
want to be?
Um
and you know, this sort of advice
is good for all aspects of life, really.
Like,
like, if I keep if I keep, you know,
just allowing things to be the way they
are, am I going to be okay with that? Or
do I need to do something? Do I need to
So, it's like a little interrupts, you
know, in your
life reflection and just sort of
like, okay, is this is this where I Do I
Do I need to be coasting here? Like, do
I need to Yeah, I think
um
like in research for me, I was
always reevaluating like, okay,
you know, what I do last year and what I
do the year before and, you know,
could you know, like what do I know now
that I didn't know then and like, you
know, am I progressing? I think like
like that sort of self-evaluation
uh is crucial when you're in grad school
because, you know, once you're in a PhD
program,
there are no more like easy metrics to
gauge like how good or bad you're doing
and the truth is
you're just doing like, you know, like
like there there just isn't such a
metric. So, all you can really do is
evaluate your past self with your
present self
and compare and contrast
to to see if you're making progress with
whatever it is you want to do.
Thank you so much for your time,
Professor Williams. I really appreciate
it. Yeah, I appreciate you having me
here. Been fun. Thanks.
>> Hey, thank you for watching this
podcast. If you liked it and you want to
see the show grow, please support with a
comment or a like.
Also, if you have any recommendations
for people you want me to bring on,
please drop a comment. Guests like
Barbara Liskov, Mike Stonebraker, Mark
Booker, these were all people that I
brought on because someone left a
comment. On another note, aside from the
podcast, I'm working on building the
ergonomic keyboard that I wish existed.
Here's a glance at the prototype. It's a
split keyboard, so there's two sides. Um
this is in the case. But yeah, we
launched on Kickstarter and we hit our
goal within eight hours of launching. I
really appreciate it if you were one of
the people who grabbed one of the early
units. Um we're now working on the long
journey of building the tooling now. And
so, if you still want to pick one up,
I've left the late pledges open on
Kickstarter, so you can grab one there.
I'll put a link in the description.
Thank you again for watching the podcast
and I'll see you in the next episode.